I'm going to talk about post-conflict recovery
سأتحدث أليكم عن خطة مابعد الحرب
and how we might do post-conflict recovery better.
وكيف يمكننا أن نتعافي أفضل بعد الحرب
The record on post-conflict recovery is not very impressive.
الإرقام لمابعد الحرب لا تعجب أبداً
40 percent of all post-conflict situations,
40 % من جميع حالات مابعد الحرب،
historically, have reverted back to conflict within a decade.
تاريخياً ، ترجع لخلاف لعقد من الزمان
In fact, they've accounted for half of all civil wars.
في الحقيقة، كانت مسؤولة عن نصف الحروب الأهلية
Why has the record been so poor?
لماذا الأرقام بهذا السوء؟
Well, the conventional approach
حسناً ، المقاربة المعتادة
to post-conflict situations
لحالات مابعد الحرب
has rested on, on kind of, three principles.
قد أستقرت، على شكل ما ، من ثلاث مبادئ
The first principle is: it's the politics that matters.
المبدأ الأول ، أن السياسة هي الأهم
So, the first thing that is prioritized is politics.
إذا ، أول شي الأولوية للسياسة
Try and build a political settlement first.
حاول أن تبني تسوية سياسية أولاً
And then the second step is to say,
ثم ثاني خطوة ، أن نقول
"The situation is admittedly dangerous, but only for a short time."
" أن الحالة قد أكتشف خطرها ، ولكنها لمدى قصير
So get peacekeepers there, but get them home as soon as possible.
أذا أبعث بقوات حفظ السلام هناك، ولكن أرجعهم لبلدانهم بأسرع ما يمكن
So, short-term peacekeepers.
إذا ، قوات حفظ سلام، قصيرة المدى
And thirdly, what is the exit strategy for the peacekeepers?
ثالثاً ، ماهي إستراتيجية الخروج لقوات حفظ السلام هؤلاء ؟
It's an election.
أنها الأنتخابات
That will produce a legitimate and accountable government.
هذا سيصنع حكومة مسؤولة وشرعية
So that's the conventional approach.
أذا تلك هي المقاربة المعتادة
I think that approach denies reality.
أعتقد أن هذا الأسلوب ينافي الحقيقة
We see that there is no quick fix.
نحن نرى أنه ليس هناك أي حلول سريعة
There's certainly no quick security fix.
بالتأكيد ليس هناك أي حلول أمنية سريعة
I've tried to look at the risks of reversion to conflict,
لقد حاولت أن أنظر إلى الأخطار المرتبطة بالصراع
during our post-conflict decade.
خلال العقد الذي أعقب الصراع .
And the risks stay high throughout the decade.
والأخطار مازالت عالية طوال العقود
And they stay high regardless of the political innovations.
وهي تظل عالية مهما كان إبداع السياسة
Does an election produce an accountable and legitimate government?
هل الإنتخابات تنتج حكومة مسؤولة وشرعية ؟
What an election produces is a winner and a loser.
ما تنتجه الإنتخابات هو فائز وخاسر
And the loser is unreconciled.
والخاسر لا يرضى
The reality is that we need to reverse the sequence.
الحقيقة أنه يجب عكس الترتيب
It's not the politics first;
ليست السياسة أولاً
it's actually the politics last.
بل في الواقع السياسة أخراً
The politics become easier as the decade progresses
السياسات تصبح أسهل على مر العصور
if you're building on a foundation
إذا كنت تبني على أساس
of security and economic development --
لتطور أمني وإقتصادي
the rebuilding of prosperity.
إعادة الإعمار سيزدهر
Why does the politics get easier?
لماذا أصبحت السياسة أسهل؟
And why is it so difficult initially?
ولماذا كانت صعبه أصلاً؟
Because after years of stagnation and decline,
بسبب سنين من الركود والتدهور
the mentality of politics is that it's a zero-sum game.
عقلية السياسة ، هي لعبة المجموع الصفري
If the reality is stagnation,
إذا كانت الحقيقة هي الركود
I can only go up if you go down.
أنا فقط استطيع الصعود ، إذا هبطت أنت
And that doesn't produce a productive politics.
وهذا لا ينتج سياسات بناءة
And so the mentality has to shift from
ولهذا يجب أن تتحول العقلية من
zero-sum to positive-sum
من المجموع صفر إلى المجموع إيجابي
before you can get a productive politics.
قبل أن تحصل على سياسات بناءة
You can only get positive, that mental shift,
يمكنك فقط الحصول على الايجابية ،ذلك التغيير العقلاني
if the reality is that prosperity is being built.
إذا كانت الحقيقة أن الإزدهار قد تم بناءه
And in order to build prosperity, we need security in place.
ولنتمكن من بناء الإزدهار ، نحتاج إلى الأمن
So that is what you get when you face reality.
إذا هذا ما تحصل عليه ، عندما تواجه الحقيقة
But the objective of facing reality
ولكن الهدف من مواجهة الواقع
is to change reality.
هو تغيير هذا الواقع
And so now let me suggest
والآن دعوني أقترح
two complimentary approaches
مقاربتين متكاملتين
to changing the reality of the situations.
لتغيير حقيقة الأوضاع
The first is to recognize the interdependence
أولاً الإعتراف بالترابط بين
of three key actors, who are different actors,
ثلاث محاور مفصلية ، وهي مؤثرات مختلفة
and at the moment are uncoordinated.
و هي غير منسقة في هذه اللحظة
The first actor is the Security Council.
أول مؤثر هو مجلس الأمن
The Security Council typically has the responsibility
مجلس الأمن ببساطة هو المسؤول
for providing the peacekeepers
عن توفير قوات حفظ السلام
who build the security.
الذين يبنون الأمن
And that needs to be recognized,
ويجب الإعتراف بهذا
first of all, that peacekeeping works.
بدايةً، أن قوات حفظ السلام تعمل
It is a cost-effective approach.
أنها مقاربة فعّالة من حيث التكلفة
It does increase security.
وهي تزيد الأمن
But it needs to be done long-term.
ولكنها يجب أن تُطبق على المدي الطويل
It needs to be a decade-long approach,
تحتاج أن تكون مقاربة لعقد من الزمان
rather than just a couple of years.
فضلاً عن كونها مقاربة لبضع سنين
That's one actor, the Security Council.
هذا مؤثر واحد ، مجلس الأمن
The second actor, different cast of guys,
المؤثر الثاني ، يأتي من ممثلين مختلفين
is the donors.
هم المتبرعين
The donors provide post-conflict aid.
المتبرعون الذي يوفرون مساعدات مابعد الحرب
Typically in the past,
كما حصل في السابق
the donors have been interested in the first couple of years,
المتبرعين كانو مهتمين في السنين الأولى
and then they got bored.
ثم أصابهم الملل .
They moved on to some other situation.
ذهبوا إلى أوضاع أخرى
Post-conflict economic recovery
لإعادة إحياء الإقتصاد بعد الحرب
is a slow process.
هو عملية بطيئة
There are no quick processes in economics
ليست هناك خطط سريعة في الإقتصاديات
except decline.
ماعدا الإفلاس
You can do that quite fast.
أنت تستطيع فعل هذا سريعاً
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So the donors have to stick with this situation
إذا يجب على المتبرعين الإلتزام بهذه الأوضاع
for at least a decade.
على الأقل لعقد من الزمان
And then the third key actor
ثم المؤثر الثالث
is the post-conflict government.
هو حكومة مابعد الحرب
And there are two key things it's got to do.
وهناك شيئان مفصليان يجب فعلهما
One is it's got to do economic reform,
أولاً يجب إعادة هيكلة الإقتصاد
not fuss about the political constitution.
وليس إزعاج الدستور السياسي
It's got to reform economic policy.
ولكن عليهم إعادة هيكلة السياسات الإقتصادية
Why? Because during conflict
لماذا؟ لأنه خلال الحرب
economic policy typically deteriorates.
تتدهور السياسات الإقتصاديات
Governments snatch short-term opportunities
الحكومات تتطلع لفرص قصيرة المدى
and, by the end of the conflict, the chickens have come home to roost.
وعندما تنتهي الحرب ، يرجع الدجاج للبيت ليقيم
So this legacy of conflict is really bad economic policy.
إذا هذه الخلاف القديم هو سياسة إقتصادية سيئة
So there is a reform agenda, and there is an inclusion agenda.
هناك أجندة إصلاح ، وهناك أجنده إحتواء
The inclusion agenda doesn't come from elections.
أجندة الإحتواء لا تأتي من الإنتخابات
Elections produce a loser, who is then excluded.
الإنتخابات تنتج خاسراً، والذي يتم أستثنائه
So the inclusion agenda means genuinely
إذا أجندة الإحتواء تعني أصالةً
bringing people inside the tent.
إحضار الناس داخل الخيمة
So those three actors.
إذا هؤلاء المؤثرات الثلاث ،
And they are interdependent
وهم معتمدين على بعض
over a long term.
على المدى الطويل
If the Security Council doesn't commit to security
إذا لم يستطع مجلس الأمن الإلتزام بالأمن
over the course of a decade,
على مدى عقد من الزمان
you don't get the reassurance which produces private investment.
وأن لا ترى أي ضمان ينتج إستثمارات خاصة
If you don't get the policy reform and the aid,
و إذا لم تصلح القوانين وتحصل على المساعدات
you don't get the economic recovery,
فلن تصل الى التعافي الإقتصادي
which is the true exit strategy for the peacekeepers.
وهي إستراتيجية الخروج لقوات حفظ السلام
So we should recognize that interdependence,
إذا نحن يجب أن نعترف بهذا الترابط
by formal, mutual commitments.
رسمياً ، بإلتزامات مشتركة
The United Nations actually has a language
للأمم المتحدة لغة في الواقع
for these mutual commitments, the recognition of mutual commitments;
لمثل هذه الإتفاقات المشتركة ، والإعتراف بالإلتزامات المشتركة
it's called the language of compact.
ويطلق عليها لغة الإتفاق
And so we need a post-conflict compact.
إذا نحن نحتاج إلى إتفاق لما بعد الحرب
The United Nations even has an agency which could broker these compacts;
الأمم المتحدة لديها وكالة تتوسط في هذه الإتفاقات
it's called the Peace Building Commission.
يطلق عليها مفوضية بناء السلام
It would be ideal to have a standard set of norms
سيكون مثالياً ، أن نملك مجموعه معايير متعارف عليها
where, when we got to a post-conflict situation,
حيث ، متى وصلنا لوضع مابعد الحرب
there was an expectation of these mutual commitments
كان هناك توقعات لمثل هذه الإلتزامات المشتركة
from the three parties.
من ثلاثة أطراف
So that's idea one:
إذا هذه الفكرة الأولى
recognize interdependence.
الإعتراف بالأشياء المعتمدة على بعضها
And now let me turn to the second approach, which is complimentary.
والأن دعوني أنتقل إلى المقاربة الثانية ، وهي مكملة .
And that is to focus on a few critical objectives.
وهي بالتركيز على بعض الأهداف الملّحة
Typical post-conflict situation is a zoo
حالة مابعد الحرب عادة مثل حديقة الحيوان
of different actors with different priorities.
مختلف اللاعبين ، مع أولويات مختلفة
And indeed, unfortunately, if you navigate by needs
وبالطبع ، ولسوء الحظ ، إذا أستعرضت الإحتياجات
you get a very unfocused agenda,
ستصل لأجندة غير مرتبة
because in these situations, needs are everywhere,
لأنه في هذه الحالات ، الإحتياجات في كل مكان
but the capacity to implement change is very limited.
ولكن إمكانية تطبيق التغيير محدودة جداً
So we have to be disciplined and focus on things that are critical.
إذا يجب أن كل نكون حذرين ومركزين على الأشياء المُلّحة
And I want to suggest that in the typical post-conflict situation
وأريد أن أقترح أنه عادةً في حالات مابعد الحرب
three things are critical.
هناك ثلاث أشياء حساسة
One is jobs.
أحدها هي الوظائف
One is improvements in basic services --
وثانيها تطوير الخدمات الأساسية
especially health, which is a disaster during conflict.
خصوصاً الصحة ، والتي تكون مهزلة خلال الحرب
So jobs, health, and clean government.
إذا الوظائف ، الصحة ، وحكومة نظيفة
Those are the three critical priorities.
تلك هي ثلاث أولويات حساسة
So I'm going to talk a little about each of them.
أذا سأتكلم قليلاً عن كل منهم
Jobs.
الوظائف
What is a distinctive approach
ماهي المقاربة المميزة؟
to generating jobs in post-conflict situations?
لتوفير وظائف ما بعد الحرب ؟
And why are jobs so important?
ولماذا هي الوظائف مهمة ؟
Jobs for whom? Especially jobs for young men.
وظائف لمن ؟ وظائف خصوصاً للشبان الصغار
In post-conflict situations,
في حالات مابعد الحرب
the reason that they so often revert to conflict,
بسبب أنهم عادةً يرجعون الى الحرب
is not because elderly women get upset.
ليس بسبب غضب النساء العجائز
It's because young men get upset.
بل بسبب غضب الشباب
And why are they upset? Because they have nothing to do.
ولماذا هم غاضبون ؟ لأن ليس لديهم شي ليفعلوه .
And so we need a process of generating jobs,
أذا نحن نحتاج إلى خطوات لتوفير الوظائف
for ordinary young men, fast.
للشباب العاديين، وبسرعة
Now, that is difficult.
الآن ، هذا صعب
Governments in post-conflict situation
الحكومات في حالات مابعد الحرب
often respond by puffing up the civil service.
عادة ماتستجيب بإغراق الخدمة المدنية
That is not a good idea.
وهذه ليست فكرة جيدة
It's not sustainable.
أنها ليست مستدامة
In fact, you're building a long-term liability
في الواقع ، أنت تبني مسئولية طويلة الأمد
by inflating civil service.
بإغراق الخدمة المدنية
But getting the private sector to expand is also difficult,
ولكن جعل القطاع الخاص يتوسع كذلك صعب
because any activity which is open to international trade
لأنه كل أي نشاط مفتوح على التجارة الدولية
is basically going to be uncompetitive
سيصبح غير تنافسي
in a post-conflict situation.
في حالات مابعد الحرب
These are not environments where you can build export manufacturing.
هذه ليست بيئات حيث يمكن بناء صناعة للتصدير
There's one sector which isn't exposed to international trade,
هناك قطاع واحد لا يتأثر بالتجارة الدولية
and which can generate a lot of jobs,
والذي يمكن أن يوفر العديد من الوظائف
and which is, in any case, a sensible sector
والذي هو ، في كل الحالات ، قطاع معقول
to expand, post-conflict,
ليتوسع ، بعد الحرب
and that is the construction sector.
وهو قطاع البناء
The construction sector has a vital role,
قطاع البناء لديه دور هام
obviously, in reconstruction.
كما يبدو ، في إعادة البناء
But typically that sector has withered away during conflict.
ولكن كالعادة هذا القطاع يتدهور خلال الحرب
During conflict people are doing destruction.
خلال الحرب الناس يدمرون
There isn't any construction going on. And so the sector shrivels away.
ليس هناك أي بناء يتم . ولذا يتدهور القطاع
And then when you try and expand it,
ثم عندما تحاول توسعته
because it's shriveled away,
لأنه بدء بالإنحسار
you encounter a lot of bottlenecks.
تواجهك العديد من الإختناقات
Basically, prices soar
أساساً ، الأسعار باهظة
and crooked politicians then milk the rents from the sector,
و السياسين الفاسدين ، بعد ذلك يستأثروا بزبدة القطاع
but it doesn't generate any jobs.
ولكنها لا توفر أي وظائف
And so the policy priority is to break the bottlenecks
أذا أولوية السياسة أن تكسر الإختناقات
in expanding the construction sector.
بتوسيع قطاع الإنشاءات
What might the bottlenecks be?
ماذا يمكن أن يكون الإختناق؟
Just think what you have to do
فقط فكر في ماذا يجب عليك فعله
successfully to build a structure, using a lot of labor.
لتنجح في بناء هيكل ، بإستخدام الكثير من الأيدي العاملة
First you need access to land.
أولاً تحتاج الحصول على الأرض
Often the legal system is broken down
وعاده النظام القانوني محطّم
so you can't even get access to land.
إذا لا يمكنك حتى الحصول على أرض
Secondly you need skills,
ثانياً تحتاج للمهارات
the mundane skills of the construction sector.
المهارات المتعلقة بقطاع الإنشاءات
In post-conflict situations we don't just need Doctors Without Borders,
في حالات مابعد الحرب لا نحتاج لأطباء بلا حدود
we need Bricklayers Without Borders,
نحن نحتاج عمال بناء بلا حدود
to rebuild the skill set.
لإعادة بناء المهارات
We need firms. The firms have gone away.
نحن نحتاج إلى شركات. والشركات غادرت
So we need to encourage the growth of local firms.
إذا نحتاج أن نشجع نمو الشركات المحلية
If we do that, we not only get the jobs,
إذا فلعنا ذلك ، لن نحصل على وظائف فحسب
we get the improvements in public infrastructure,
نحصل كذلك على التطوير للبنية التحتية العامة
the restoration of public infrastructure.
ترميم البنية التحتية العامة
Let me turn from jobs to the second objective,
دعوني أنتقل من الوظائف إلى الهدف الثاني
which is improving basic social services.
وهو تطوير الخدمات الإجتماعية الأساسية
And to date, there has been a sort of a schizophrenia
ولحد تاريخنا هذا ، هناك نوع من الإنفصام
in the donor community,
في مجتمع المتبرعين ،
as to how to build basic services
حول كيفية بناء الخدمات الأساسية
in post-conflict sectors.
في قطاعات مابعد الحرب
On the one hand it pays lip service
في جانب تدفع ضريبة كلامية
to the idea of rebuild an effective state
نحو فكرة إعادة بناء دولة فعالة
in the image of Scandinavia in the 1950s.
عند تصورنا لإسكندانافيا في الخمسينات
Lets develop line ministries of this, that, and the other,
دعونا نطور وزارات صفية لعمل هذا وذلك وتلكم
that deliver these services.
والتي توصل هذه الخدمات
And it's schizophrenic because in their hearts
وهو أنفصامي لأنه في داخل قلوبهم
donors know that's not a realistic agenda,
يعرف المتبرعون أنها ليست أجندة واقعية
and so what they also do is the total bypass:
وبذلك فأن ما يفعلونه هو التجاوز الكلي
just fund NGOs.
فقط أدعم المنظمات الغير حكومية
Neither of those approaches is sensible.
كلٌ من هذه الأساليب ليس منطقياً
And so what I'd suggest
لذا ما أقترحه
is what I call Independent Service Authorities.
هو ما أسميه الجهات الرسمية المستقلة
It's to split the functions of a monopoly line ministry up into three.
وهو أن نقسم المهام الإحتكارية للوزارات الصفية إلى ثلاثة صفوف
The planning function and policy function stays with the ministry;
مهمة التخطيط والتشريع تظل مع الوزارة
the delivery of services on the ground,
أما توصيل الخدمات على الأرض
you should use whatever works --
يجب أن تستخدم أي شي يعمل
churches, NGOs, local communities,
الكنائس ، المنظمات الغير ربحية ، المجتمعات المحلية
whatever works.
أي جهة تنفذ
And in between, there should be a public agency,
وفي هذه الغضون ، يجب أن يكون هناك وكالة قومية
the Independent Service Authority,
الجهة المستقلة المسؤولة عن الخدمات
which channels public money,
والتي توصل المال العام
and especially donor money,
وخصوصاً أموال المتبرعين
to the retail providers.
إلى مقدمي الخدمات بالتجزئة
So the NGOs become part of a public government system,
إذا المنظمات الغير ربحية تصبح جزء من نظام الحكومة
rather than independent of it.
بدلاً عن كونها مستقلة عنه
One advantage of that is that you can allocate money coherently.
أحد الفضائل لذلك أنه يمكنك توزيع الأموال بمنطقية
Another is, you can make NGOs accountable.
والأخر هو ، أنه يمكنك أن تجعل المنظمات مُحاسبة ومسؤولة
You can use yardstick competition,
يمكنك أن تستخدم معيار المنافسة
so they have to compete against each other
إذا يجب عليهم أن يتنافسوا فيما بينهم
for the resources.
من أجل الموارد
The good NGOs, like Oxfam, are very keen on this idea.
الجهات الجيدة ، مثل أوكسفام ، مصممين جداً على هذه الفكرة
They want to have the discipline and accountability.
أنهم يريدون المسئولية والمحاسبة
So that's a way to get basic services scaled up.
إذا هذه طريقة لرفع مستوى الخدمات الأساسية
And because the government would be funding it,
ولأن الدولة ستمولها
it would be co-branding these services.
ستتمتع بميزات الماركة التجارية سوياً
So they wouldn't be provided thanks to
إذا لا يتوجب عليهم تقديم الشكر ل
the United States government and some NGO.
حكومة الولايات المتحدة ، وبعض المنظمات الغير ربحية
They would be co-branded
سيتشاركون الماركة التجارية
as being done by the post-conflict government, in the country.
و كأنها أُنجزت من قبل حكومة مابعد الحرب ، في الدولة
So, jobs, basic services, finally, clean government.
إذا الوظائف ، الخدمات الأساسية ، وأخيراً حكومة نظيفة
Clean means follow their money.
نظيفة بمعنى تتبع أموالها
The typical post-conflict government is so short of money
كالعادة حكومات مابعد الحرب تفتقر للمال
that it needs our money
وأنها تحتاج لأموالنا
just to be on a life-support system.
فقط لتبقي النظام على قيد الحياة
You can't get the basic functions of the state done
لا تستطيع أن تنهي الأعمال الأساسية للحكومة
unless we put money into the core budget of these countries.
مالم يكون المال في صميم ميزانية هذه الدول
But, if we put money into the core budget,
ولكن إذا وضعنا المال في صميم الميزانية
we know that there aren't the budget systems with integrity
نحن نعلم أنه ليس هناك نظام ميزانية بالنزاهة
that mean that money will be well spent.
التي تضمن أن ينفق المال في مكانه
And if all we do is put money in and close our eyes
أما إذا كان ماتفعله هو وضع المال وإغماض عينيك
it's not just that the money is wasted --
ليس فقط سيضيع ذلك المال
that's the least of the problems --
هذه أقل المشاكل ،
it's that the money is captured.
بل سيحصل على المال
It's captured by the crooks who are at the heart of the political problem.
سيحصل عليه المحتالين الذين هم قلب المشكلة السياسية
And so inadvertently we empower the people who are the problem.
وبذا دون أن ندري نحن نقوّي الناس الذين هم أساساً المشكلة
So building clean government means, yes, provide money
إذا بناء حكومة نظيفة يعني ، نعم ، قدّم مالاً
to the budget,
لأجل الميزانية
but also provide a lot of scrutiny,
ولكن أيضاً توفير الكثير من التدقيق
which means a lot of technical assistance that follows the money.
والذي يعني الكثير من المساعده التقنية التي تتبع المال
Paddy Ashdown, who was the grand high nabob of Bosnia
بادي أشداون ، والذي كان المبعوث السامي في بوسنيا
to the United Nations,
للأمم المتحدة
in his book about his experience, he said,
في كتابه عن خبراته ، قال
"I realize what I needed
أدركت أن ما أحتاجه
was accountants without borders,
هو محاسبين بلا حدود
to follow that money."
ليتابعوا ذلك المال
So that's the -- let me wrap up,
إذاً -- دعوني أعيد الترتيب
this is the package.
هذه هي الحزمة
What's the goal?
ما هو الهدف ؟
If we follow this, what would we hope to achieve?
إذا أتبعنا ذلك ، ما الذي نأمله أن يتحقق ؟
That after 10 years,
أنه بعد عشر سنوات ،
the focus on the construction sector
التركيز على قطاع الإنشاءات
would have produced both jobs
يكون قد وفر الأثنان الوظائف
and, hence, security --
وعليه، الأمان
because young people would have jobs --
لأنه الشباب سيجدون وظائف
and it would have reconstructed the infrastructure.
وتكون قد أعدت ترميم البنية التحتية
So that's the focus on the construction sector.
أذاً التركيز على قطاع الإنشاءات
The focus on the basic service delivery
التركيز على توصيل الخدمات الأساسية
through these independent service authorities
من خلال هذه الجهات الخدمية المستقلة
would have rescued basic services
والتي أنقذت الخدمات الأساسية
from their catastrophic levels,
من حالاتها المأساوية
and it would have given ordinary people
وحتما ستعطي الناس العاديون
the sense that the government was doing something useful.
الأحساس بأن الحكومة كانت تفعل شيئا نافعاً
The emphasis on clean government
التركيز على حكومة نظيفة
would have gradually squeezed out the political crooks,
سيتمكن تدريجياً من تقليص المشاكل السياسية
because there wouldn't be any money
لأنه لن يكون هناك مالاً
in taking part in the politics.
سيأخذ دوراً في السياسة
And so gradually the selection,
وكذلك تدريجياً الإنتخاب
the composition of politicians,
لبوتقة من السياسين
would shift from the crooked to the honest.
سينقلنا من الإستغلال إلى الأمانة
Where would that leave us?
وأين سيتركنا ذلك ؟
Gradually it would shift
تدريجياً سينتقل
from a politics of plunder
من سياسة السلب والنهب
to a politics of hope. Thank you.
إلى سياسة الأمل ، شكراً لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)